Abrams, Albert J.; Papers apap056
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Albert J. Abrams Papers
1961, 1964-1965, 1970-1976, 1980
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Abrams, Albert J.
apap056
0.75 cubic ft.
Albert Jack Abrams was born in Stamford, Connecticut, on May 29, 1915. Abrams began his university studies at the University of Michigan in 1932, and he attended the National Institute for Public Affairs in Washington, D.C., in 1935. He received an A.B. from New York University in 1936, and he continued his studies at Columbia University (1940) and the Cornell School of Labor and Industrial Relations (1946). The records in this manuscript collection were originally arranged in a numerically classified subject file under the general subject of legislative administration.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Biographical Sketch
Albert Jack Abrams was born in Stamford, Connecticut, on May 29, 1915. Abrams began his university studies at the University of Michigan in 1932, and he attended the National Institute for Public Affairs in Washington, D.C., in 1935. He received an A.B. from New York University in 1936, and he continued his studies at Columbia University (1940) and the Cornell School of Labor and Industrial Relations (1946).[1]
He married Ruth Elsie Weinert on March 7, 1943, and they had three children: David, Eugenie, and Valerie.His first wife died in 1959.On December 16, 1967, Abrams married Lorena Friedman Kessler, a widow who had one adult son, Marc.[2]
Albert J. Abrams was a lecturer at the Vassar Summer Institute and other universities, and he taught a seminar on legislative administration at the Graduate School of Public Affairs, at SUNY, Albany, in 1975.In 1936, while still attending New York University, Abrams worked in the New York State Senate as a research assistant to Senator Thomas circa Desmond of Newburgh.[3] He was the director of the New York State Joint Legislative Committee on Problems of Aging (1947-58), city manager of Newburgh, NY (1958-60), and director of social and economic planning for the New York State Senate (1960-62).[4] Abrams served in the Senate as a special assistant (1960-61) and then executive assistant (1961-62) to Senate Majority Leader Walter J. Mahoney. Abrams was elected Secretary of the Senate on January 6, 1963, and was re-elected to the post in January 1966.[5] He continued as Secretary until 1976.
The American Society for Public Administration awarded Abrams the Governor Alfred E. Smith award for "outstanding administrative achievement in a staff position" in 1964.[6] A member of the American Society for Public Administration, Abrams served as the president of the Capital District Chapter in 1968.[7]
Abrams wrote articles on public administration for technical journals and also explained the workings of the legislative process to the generalpublic through articles in popular magazines.[8] Abrams also wrotearticles for the Delmar Spotlight of humorous anecdotes and his take on the century.
Albert J. Abrams died in 1993.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized alphabetically. There are no series.
Scope and Contents
The records in this manuscript collection were originally arranged in a numerically classified subject file under the general subject of legislative administration. This filing system was never completely utilized (most of the folders were empty because no documents fitting the descriptions for those folders were ever created) and there was no key that explained the numbers, so there has been no attempt to maintain that filing system. However, most folders retain the originally assigned titles. The folders have been rearranged in alphabetical order to simplify searching.
Since Abrams worked in legislative administration and also taught about it (through articles and through classes he taught), his ideas about the subject are well considered and of interest to someone researching the subject. Beyond this, the papers offer a glimpse into the day-to-day running of the New York State Senate, such as handling the Senate's internal budget, space allocation, maintenance, security and personnel. Abrams looked at legislative bills from the standpoint of what these cost to print and how to handle the physical volume of these bills, rather than that of the intended legislative effect. These papers also contain some files on personal interrelations among legislators, which are interesting given the effect that such matters can have on the passage of bills.The most interesting of these is "Socialization of Senators Within the Senate Chamber" (1975), which tallies up conversations between senators and names those initiating and receiving conversations.
This series contains copies of essays, staff reports, newspaper clippings, notes, memoranda, photographs and correspondence pertaining to Abrams' work as secretary of the New York State Senate. This series includes files on aspects of administrating the functions of the senate, essays he wrote on legislative administration, and teaching material from a course he taught on legislative administration in 1975. The papers also contain some published material, such as senate handbooks.
For further information on Abrams, a researcher should refer to the records of American Society for Public Administration--Capital District Chapter. These records do not contain his president's records, but there is at least one printed message from him found in the chapter's 1968 annual report.
Acquisition Information
Albert J. Abrams donated these papers to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections in a series of donations in the 1980s.
Public Servants; Public Affairs Committee; Legislative and Policy series; Legislative Records; Administrative Regulations; Bills; Financial Records; Senate Records; Albert J. Abrams
- American Society of Legislative Clerks and Secretaries, 1972; 1980 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 1)
- Broadcasting of Legislative Sessions, 1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 2)
- Budgets for Legislature, 1966-1967; 1973 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 3)
- Campaigns of 1970 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 4)
- Chisholm, Shirley--Profile, ca.1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 5)
- Codes of Ethics, ca. (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 6)
- Committees--Administration, ca.1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 7)
- "The Common Good: New York State's Legislature in Action"--Film Teaching Guide, 1964 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 8)
- Computer Systems--Administration, 1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 9)
- Debate Strategies, ca.1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 10)
- Dinner Program, 1966 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 11)
- "Guide to Legislative Administration,", 1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 12)
- "Guide to State Legislators: What Every Federal Administrator Should Know,", ca.1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 13)
- "Guidelines to Better Legislative Administration,", ca.1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 14)
- Joint Senate-Assembly Operations, ca.1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 15)
- Junkets, ca.1970 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 16)
- "Legislative Administration,", 1971 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 17)
- Legislative Administration, 1974 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 18)
- "The Legislative Administrator,", 1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 19)
- Legislative Bills, 1972-73 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 20)
- Legislative Bills, 1974 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 21)
- Legislative Bills--Printing, 1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 22)
- Legislative Bills--Volume, ca.1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 23)
- "Legislative Innovation: A Selected Annotated Bibliography,", 1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 24)
- Legislative Organization, 1973 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 25)
- Legislative Process, ca.1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 26)
- Legislative Reform--Folder 1, 1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 27)
- Legislative Reform--Folder 2, 1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 28)
- Legislative Salaries and Prequisites, 1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 29)
- Legislative Security, 1972 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 30)
- Legislative Session--Length, 1970 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 31)
- Legislature, 1974; 1976 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 32)
- Legislature, 1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 33)
- Legislature--Administrative Environment, 1964-1965; 1975 (Box 1 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 34)
- Let Us Pray--Prayers from Opening Sessions of New York Senate, 1973 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 1)
- Lulus, 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 2)
- Mailing List Development and Maintenance, 1966; 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 3)
- "Manual of Procedure for the Senate Document Rooms,", 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 4)
- National Conference of State Legislative Leaders, 1961 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 5)
- Openness in Government, ca.1970 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 6)
- Organization and Procedures Manual for New York State Senate, 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 7)
- Orientation on Procedures, Services and Policies, 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 8)
- Parliaments, 1972 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 9)
- Payroll--Administration, 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 10)
- "Pennsylvania Coal and Electrical Energy Independence for the Northeast,", ca.1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 11)
- Personnel--Administration, 1973 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 12)
- Personnel in Senate, 1973 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 13)
- Photographs, ca.1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 14)
- Political Values, 1973 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 15)
- Program Development, 1970 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 16)
- Public Relations, 1961; 1972; 1974 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 17)
- Reapportionment, ca.1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 18)
- "A Report on Albany Library Resources for Programs in Legislative Development,", ca.1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 19)
- Rivalries Within the House, 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 20)
- "Rules and Rulings" of the New York State Senate, ca.1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 21)
- "Rules of the Senate,", 1974 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 22)
- Salary Standardization, ca.1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 23)
- Scandals, 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 24)
- Security in Chambers, 1973 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 25)
- Seminar on Legislative Administration--Papers and Exam Questions, 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 26)
- Seminar on Legislative Administration--Readings, 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 27)
- Seminar on Legislative Administration--Syllabus, 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 28)
- Senate/Assembly Adversary Relationship, 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 29)
- Senate and House Apportionment by State and Seat Population, 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 30)
- "Socialization of Senators Within the Senate Chamber,", 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 31)
- "The Staff of Liberty,", 1970 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 32)
- Staff Training, 1974 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 33)
- Tensions Between Executive and Legislative Branches, 1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 34)
- "Women in the Legislature,", ca.1975 (Box 2 (Albert J. Abrams Papers), Folder 35)